Speaker 0: It's Monday February 10th 2025.
Speaker 0: I'm rim I'm scared and this is geek nights tonight.
Speaker 0: We are talking about electronic payments.
Speaker 1: Let's do this.
Speaker 0: So we missed some geek nights because of course we were in mag fest And we don't like to do a bunch of shows right before we go to a con.
Speaker 0: I got sick at mag fest which what with what turned out to be flu a Just I got less.
Speaker 1: I got less sick at mag fest which was probably also flu a yup flu Seems to have made the rounds.
Speaker 1: I was much less sick than rim, but a tiny mucus remains.
Speaker 1: Yes.
Speaker 0: And the worst thing is I looked up the.
Speaker 0: the incubation period for the current flu way is one to four days.
Speaker 0: So either I was exposed at work then came to mag fest then got sick Or I was exposed at mag fest because I spent most of the first day hanging out with other people and not you.
Speaker 0: so I didn't.
Speaker 1: I didn't feel any symptom until like What after getting home from mag fest?
Speaker 0: it was dark like you saw.
Speaker 0: I was at mag fest like I was going full steam And then the second night I was like oh, I'm tired I'm gonna go to bed early so I went to bed at like midnight instead of like staying out late crazy.
Speaker 0: And the next day we do our panel and then after the panel I just I'm tired so I go take a nap and then I wake up and I got a fever and I feel like shit, and then I barg a little while later, and then I just went the fuck home.
Speaker 1: Meanwhile I had to then do the Sunday panel.
Speaker 0: Panel is cursed.
Speaker 0: This is three conventions in a row where we scheduled that panel And I get sick and you have to do it by yourself.
Speaker 0: I think we must never panels too long.
Speaker 1: I got to remove even more games, but it regardless that I was like uh you know It's the end of mag fest whatever and it's like people are filling up the room because there is nothing else to do and they're still At mag fest, and I'm like why are you people still here?
Speaker 1: God I'm here because I have to be What's your excuse?
Speaker 0: but also like you can't deny people do like at mag fest this mag fest in particular?
Speaker 0: I'll just say the our rooms were pretty full and people seemed to really enjoy our talks And it was a lot of people who've never seen our stuff before.
Speaker 1: I guess that you know.
Speaker 1: It seems to be what happens because people have seen our stuff.
Speaker 1: Don't come back.
Speaker 0: Yeah, cuz they know better.
Speaker 0: They know it'll be on YouTube and they know if the panel was bad It won't appear on YouTube in which case they definitely didn't want to be there.
Speaker 0: So uh yeah, there's a lot of news.
Speaker 0: We're not gonna cover everything, but I got a thing it will be here.
Speaker 1: But if we tried to cover all the news news would happen faster than we could cover it.
Speaker 0: yep.
Speaker 0: So I got one news and it is kind of a big deal, but it's also kind of a cool technology thing.
Speaker 0: So if you didn't know the Baltic states Latvia Lithuania, Estonia Cool countries a lot in some ways yeah in other ways not so cool, but you know well I mean you could say that about a lot all countries.
Speaker 0: There's no country.
Speaker 0: That's just cool.
Speaker 1: I mean at this point.
Speaker 1: You know it's like it's hard to talk when our country is went from you know Way down the cool list right out.
Speaker 1: So it's like you know what it's like.
Speaker 1: yeah, I could.
Speaker 1: I could point out a lot of bad things about some Baltic states But they if they point the finger back.
Speaker 1: I'd be like oh yep.
Speaker 1: You're right.
Speaker 1: Yep.
Speaker 1: We're worse now We weren't but now we are.
Speaker 0: but as you know Russia had invaded Ukraine in 2014 and that war is ongoing And like it's a whole big thing.
Speaker 0: But what you might not have known is that Latvia Lithuania and Estonia are very much aligned with the West with Europe with NATO.
Speaker 0: They are trying to be good democratic countries with varying levels of success, but the cool places.
Speaker 0: But because of their history and because of their geographic location Despite the fact that Russia is for all intents and purposes at war with NATO Their power grids were the same as the Russian power grid like the old Soviet grid.
Speaker 0: So that puts them in a lot of dangers you can imagine.
Speaker 0: and also the Russian power grid is not shall we say?
Speaker 1: Great.
Speaker 0: Also their ally Ukraine is repeatedly attacking Russia's power grid which could have the side effect of fucking up their power.
Speaker 0: So they have been working for a long time on a massive Project like this is on the level of that dog in H Where a bunch of countries one day shifted from driving on the wrong side of the road to driving on the correct side of the road.
Speaker 0: They detached themselves From the Russian and Belarusian power grid and have attached themselves to the EU's power grid.
Speaker 0: Yeah There's I'm sure I feel like of all people practical engineering.
Speaker 0: at some point like a few months from now We'll have a video that explains like how the fuck they did that Because it's crazy that they did.
Speaker 1: everyone's power have to go out like a Dagon H Everyone.
Speaker 1: it was like, you know, they had to stop driving and then so it was crazy what they did.
Speaker 0: there's some videos you can find online if you look hard enough of like specific switching stations like doing the thing with these like 15 foot long arms swinging around it looks like things are exploding.
Speaker 0: but they basically Shifted for 24 hours to having a completely independent power grid powered entirely within their own nation.
Speaker 0: I see was a stretch.
Speaker 1: and then they integrated that guess they don't have enough power plants for that.
Speaker 0: I mean almost nobody has no power plants for that like, okay.
Speaker 0: And then they switched to being connected to the you the US power arts the US the NATO power grid.
Speaker 0: Very similarly to how the US actually has a bunch of different Semi-independent power grids that have interconnects between them except our fucking state of Texas Which has its own power grid because it's basically a hostile power Mm-hmm.
Speaker 0: So this is like forget geopolitics in the war and all that stuff.
Speaker 0: What I want to focus on for geek nights Monday is the sheer operational and Engineering feat that this was cannot be overstated.
Speaker 1: This is like, I don't know I don't know much about like.
Speaker 1: what are the what's like?
Speaker 1: the voltage and amps on their outlets outlet shape?
Speaker 1: It's like, you know, just everyone have to go and buy new adapters or they is it compatible with?
Speaker 0: it's compatible.
Speaker 0: They just shifted the power grid and I don't know all the details of how they pulled this off.
Speaker 0: Like I'm mostly working on news articles.
Speaker 0: Nobody has made a nice detailed explainer yet of exactly what went down.
Speaker 0: hmm So yeah, anyway got any news?
Speaker 1: Yeah, so there's this game.
Speaker 1: This game has been a big deal for a long time like a huge huge deal and people don't talk about it enough.
Speaker 1: I first found out about it freshman year of college because my roommate played it incessantly.
Speaker 1: It's football manager.
Speaker 1: Yeah, there's a lot of manager games out there.
Speaker 1: But football manager is like the first one Effectively the first one and that was a big deal and all the other ones are imitators and it's still the biggest one, right?
Speaker 1: I've tried to play a few other managers.
Speaker 1: I tried to play like an f1 manager one time It sucks is the kind of games that like.
Speaker 1: if I did prison prison simulator is basically sort of the same kind of game.
Speaker 0: effectively Imagine rim no changes except I do not have to work to live.
Speaker 0: I'd be all-in on that kind of game.
Speaker 1: Yeah, so it's basically you just pretend that you're a the manager of a soccer team and you're just like running numbers.
Speaker 1: It's like spreadsheet the game and you know, it's.
Speaker 1: it's the same kind of play a soccer fire FIFA You just.
Speaker 0: it's the same kind of game of hearts of iron where you're just like run the system of a country during World War two.
Speaker 1: Yep, now this game is so big and so successful and so popular that they can afford to do this.
Speaker 1: But what they've done is they said look we're working on you know, a new game every year like we do and football manager 25.
Speaker 1: We've been working on it.
Speaker 1: And honestly, it is not up to our standards.
Speaker 1: Like it's just not good enough.
Speaker 1: And so what they decided to do is they said look, we're just not gonna release any football manager 25.
Speaker 1: There won't be such a game.
Speaker 1: It's canceled.
Speaker 1: We're gonna make football manager 26 next year.
Speaker 1: Keep playing football manager 24 for the year.
Speaker 1: That is 2025 and we'll be back And that's kind of crazy.
Speaker 0: I wish more companies had the courage to do that kind of thing, right?
Speaker 1: Because well a they're so successful they can afford to do that true but secondly You see so many companies out there who just don't do this when they probably should.
Speaker 1: and it's like up.
Speaker 1: Here's a new, you know, I guess to make a more close comparison EA Sports is the new FIFA.
Speaker 1: It's 90% the same as the old one.
Speaker 1: Yeah, we just do our yearly cash grab because we can we find some way to force you to buy it Even if it's not a big improvement.
Speaker 0: Yeah, I remember reading the thing about how a lot of people skip several years in a row of all those kinds of games Because they're really not different right, and so Here's people who are doing it, you know, not just game wise but software wise.
Speaker 1: it's like yeah You're only going to you know, release your new version if you feel It's a significant upgrade over the previous version and that it's a quality piece of software.
Speaker 1: You don't come out with some piece of shit product and ruin your reputation.
Speaker 1: They're playing the long game here And I'm sure there are some fans who are gonna be disappointed that they're just gonna be playing the same game for another year instead Of getting a new one.
Speaker 1: They all thought was coming.
Speaker 1: Mmm, but on the other hand In the long better game, yeah, it's like you're gonna get some.
Speaker 1: you know, you're not gonna Imagine this Adobe.
Speaker 1: what those fans who were disappointed?
Speaker 1: Imagine if the shitty version of 25 came out, they'd be like, oh this thing sucks, right?
Speaker 0: Well, I can edge if Adobe instead of the buggy as hell CS 4 had come out if they had just been like look CS 4 isn't ready.
Speaker 0: So just hold out and then you can buy CS 5 in eight more months and it won't be buggy as shit.
Speaker 0: Like that would have just been better for me.
Speaker 1: Yeah, yeah, this is uh, I think other companies that have the money to get away with this Should you know take note and let's all let's see how well they do in 2026, right?
Speaker 0: And so because they could fail as an experiment.
Speaker 0: but like, you know, my day job is being a product manager.
Speaker 0: I've been a product manager for a long goddamn time and The number of companies that I will like even internally for things that are not public will be like This is the day you committed to so fucking deliver it on this date and never having the courage to
Speaker 1: arbitrary Nonsense
Speaker 0: arbitrary like hey, would it really be that bad if we waited four more months?
Speaker 1: And then listen was people don't remember that half-life 1 was delayed Incessantly and they said they you know, they were like, you know what?
Speaker 1: It'll be ready when it's ready.
Speaker 1: and hey That seemed to work out very well Right.
Speaker 1: It's so if I ever make software It's like there may be some realities that forced me to do things like hey, I'm running out of money I can't afford to pay anyone anymore.
Speaker 1: We haven't we're not ready yet.
Speaker 1: Oops, but I'm not.
Speaker 1: there will not be Arbitrary requirements of nonsense, right?
Speaker 1: It's like we're gonna release when we're ready and we have quality and something that's worth someone paying money for Because that is historically been a recipe for success when you have enough money to get to the finish line.
Speaker 0: Yeah.
Speaker 0: So one last little news.
Speaker 0: everyone's annoyed about How about AI and machine learning in general?
Speaker 0: But specifically that if you go to Google and you search for stuff There's these AI summaries at the top of the results generally and those results are often just wrong or bad Like they're the wrong information.
Speaker 1: I see I I don't.
Speaker 1: I don't look at those and I you know using Google.
Speaker 1: but the point is I think it's actually a benefit to have those because They turn into funny memes that we me when other people share them and that is that is good that that I will agree with that.
Speaker 0: But what's really funny is that all the company's doing this generative stuff in a public space especially like generic prompts like a random Google search.
Speaker 0: The thing they're struggling with is that it's real easy to get these things to make porn for you As we saw that thing a little while ago with the Amazon chat bot where someone got it to start role-playing with them in a in a very sexy way, so The companies are terrified of this.
Speaker 0: They're also terrified of Certain kinds of like racist and sexist things appearing because then they get in trouble about it.
Speaker 0: I don't think these companies actually care about the racism.
Speaker 0: I think they care about the public image of the racism.
Speaker 0: Okay, some point like if you use Adobe's image generation You can't make it make someone who looks sad nor can you make it make someone of a particular gender or race?
Speaker 1: Like it's always the real thing that they're afraid of is not just the perception It's that you can't sell a product to businesses if it's not not safe for work.
Speaker 0: Yep, and What someone has discovered and I've tested this and it works if you just add the word fucking To any Google search that AI summary never appears.
Speaker 0: They've clearly put that word on a list.
Speaker 0: But as an aside and this is something I haven't found any reporting on it, but I discovered it YouTube now if you're a YouTube creator has a page where in your studio you get it'll suggest Hey make a video about this and it gives you this terrible looking thumbnail that it makes up with generative AI and a description And they're all like the mood.
Speaker 0: every one of them is basically just the mr.
Speaker 0: Beast burger like they are just awful awful Pro-capitalist fucked up things.
Speaker 1: What if you Like me, I'm sure someone's already doing this make a channel and just do whatever it tells you to and see how successful that is.
Speaker 0: We could but these aren't like so bad.
Speaker 0: They're funny.
Speaker 0: They're just.
Speaker 0: they're so like generic AI mishmash crap.
Speaker 0: What I actually want to do is generate one of these and then make a video that just be saying yeah Look at this fucking Google thing.
Speaker 0: It's terrible.
Speaker 0: This is what Google wanted me to make a video about and that's the description that's there and you clicked on this.
Speaker 0: cuz you're dumb.
Speaker 0: But I discovered something specific.
Speaker 0: the word capitalism in any context even by itself Prevents it from returning results.
Speaker 0: Mm-hmm anything I put in war crime nonsense I put in all sorts of stuff even like negative things about communism and it would recommend a ton of videos we could make.
Speaker 0: but If the word capitalism is in it, it will not recommend anything no matter what it just says.
Speaker 0: Sorry couldn't give you a recommendation and I found that very specific and interesting Because there were not many other terms that other than the ones you would expect that would not return results.
Speaker 1: that were Hey Maybe they just don't want people to make videos promoting capitalist.
Speaker 0: I mean one could hope but the first thing I typed in when that prompt appeared was how game theory and hide like and Destroying capitalism and it wouldn't give me any results.
Speaker 0: But anyway things of the day.
Speaker 0: So we bumped into this last night randomly.
Speaker 0: It's a video from.
Speaker 0: it was only uploaded 13 days ago But the person who made it from Chechia made it in 2020.
Speaker 0: It is a 14-minute animated short.
Speaker 1: that is absolutely delightful because one animated shorts are getting too long.
Speaker 0: Well, I was worried because you know, we had some family over and they were like, oh, what's that video?
Speaker 0: Let's watch it.
Speaker 1: I'm not picking on this video specifically because I haven't even watched it but there has been a trend lately.
Speaker 1: We're like Shorts at.
Speaker 1: Oh film festivals both animated and non have been increasing in length.
Speaker 0: as Someone who is a member of a Siva East and like like gets to vote on the judging of the screening Yeah, some of those things were like approaching too long But also like student films used to be like enemy.
Speaker 1: I think they need to make a new category.
Speaker 1: I think the shorts should be like five maybe even three minutes or less and then we should make a new category the mids Which is you're not a full-length feature, but you're also not a short.
Speaker 1: It's a big like if it's anywhere between you know, 45 minutes and you know Five minutes.
Speaker 0: Yeah, that's a mid but I was pleasantly surprised by this one because one a lot of its theme Was very like secretive Kells adjacent and also like the way it's framed like that kind of work.
Speaker 0: But the characters look exactly like they were designed by our old friend grickle Mmm, it was.
Speaker 0: it was actually really worth watching.
Speaker 0: sounds between the crowns.
Speaker 1: All right.
Speaker 1: So this video.
Speaker 1: I think the thumbnail for this video might be a high gender But regardless the video itself has quality content that is not AI generated in any way shape or form that I can tell.
Speaker 1: and what's going on here is They're playing ghosts and goblins for the NES which is you know a game that has some issues a lot of good ideas But not a good game.
Speaker 1: I would say right the the original arcade game was way better.
Speaker 1: the NES port runs slowly.
Speaker 1: I didn't realize this but yet the reason it feels like it runs slowly and laggy all the time is because They basically cut the frame rate from 60 to 20 because they can't process all of the things that needs to process in The time it takes to render one frame.
Speaker 1: so they just made the whole game slower and set the frame rate to 20 FPS and then they have three frames of time to do all the processing and even then the game like has slowdowns and like Flicker that is worse than super dodgeball.
Speaker 1: Yeah And so this happens.
Speaker 1: a lot of NES games though, even like Zelda 1, right?
Speaker 1: I mean made by Nintendo.
Speaker 1: if you go to the top left of the map There's a bunch of Lionel's up there and you get hit.
Speaker 1: it's a game and the line will shoot their swords up at the same Time.
Speaker 0: Yeah, there's too many Room with a lot of dark knots.
Speaker 0: you get that little like dit to dit stutter when you try to walk in.
Speaker 1: Yeah, Mega Man 2 has some you know lag areas that can happen, especially if you get hit and stuff.
Speaker 1: So it's not like, you know, well all games are immune for this, but this game in particular is really bad and It turns out it's like yeah.
Speaker 1: Because that's such a symptom of so many NES games even top tier ones.
Speaker 1: I just as always just took for granted that it's like yeah.
Speaker 1: It's because the NES can only do so much and people are making it do More than it could do and that was the side effect was that sometimes lag.
Speaker 1: it turns out that some games not all but some programmed poorly Programmed very poorly.
Speaker 1: Yeah, and so in this video this person shows how they can make a patches to Ghosts and goblins for the NES and Get the frame rate up without changing the game in any way other than getting the frame rate up which obviously makes the game You know different, you know in a way but but not
Speaker 0: like otherwise Made the game better but also had to like change aspects of the game to free up space and cycles to do other things Right.
Speaker 1: Normally it's like okay I freed up some memory by making some sprites smaller or reducing color depth or you know, something like that.
Speaker 1: No, this doesn't change the game in any way.
Speaker 1: They just change the code To be better and fit it in the same memory with the same hardware.
Speaker 1: They just made the ROM better and On their channel, they have some other content of this nature and it's like damn.
Speaker 1: now I really want someone to go out and release like, you know patch ROMs of old Games that don't change the ROM in any way.
Speaker 1: That's other than Get.
Speaker 1: if the frame rate is less than 60 get it up to 60 and also if there are lags remove the lags if possible.
Speaker 1: But otherwise don't change the games.
Speaker 1: Just make them Better.
Speaker 1: performance fixes don't fix the bugs even right.
Speaker 1: if there's bugs, you know that cause weird behaviors.
Speaker 1: You got to keep those in.
Speaker 1: we're just talking about performance only Improvements, you know doing that to these kind of.
Speaker 1: I guess if the game runs at 60 FPS consistently You don't need to patch it.
Speaker 0: I think that these kinds of projects would be good group projects for certain kinds of programming classes?
Speaker 1: Yeah for sure, but you know if you need to learn NES assembler, yeah.
Speaker 0: So at the moment we were at mag fest 2025. a video of the panel Emily and I did Metacontacts post post modernism and games is on YouTube with the slides.
Speaker 0: We got a pretty strong response to that panel.
Speaker 0: So More content is coming on that.
Speaker 0: the other panel.
Speaker 0: Take your fucking turn We didn't video cuz there's video of us doing that panel from unplugged.
Speaker 0: so go find that.
Speaker 0: and the new panel that we have video Of every game is the same game.
Speaker 0: I will have edited it up probably Within a week or so now that I'm back.
Speaker 0: I did it.
Speaker 1: I did that pass the second time.
Speaker 1: I did that panel by myself.
Speaker 0: Yeah, I got.
Speaker 0: at least I did that panel with you this time.
Speaker 1: Yeah.
Speaker 1: So speaking of packs packs East is thankfully may nice Through 11th, it's not gonna be fucking cold Thanks Satan because the restaurants over nearby a part of started to disappear.
Speaker 0: So it'll be nice to walk over to that Mexican place.
Speaker 0: That's like way on the other side.
Speaker 1: I don't know if that place is still there, but I actually haven't checked.
Speaker 1: I don't think it is.
Speaker 1: but the point is it's gonna be warmer.
Speaker 1: It should be warmer because it's in May but early bird pricing ended February 7th.
Speaker 1: So now the price of the packs East badge has gone up Or at least it says on the website buy your badges before February 7th to lock in early bird pricing and it's February 10th As I record this.
Speaker 1: But yeah, I don't know.
Speaker 1: maybe they haven't updated the prey.
Speaker 1: Oh, yeah, I think they have.
Speaker 1: I don't know.
Speaker 1: regardless I'm out of buy it sooner.
Speaker 1: I don't know if prices will go up.
Speaker 0: more packs East should be fun time.
Speaker 0: and Also, I've got to do a little.
Speaker 0: I'm adding a bit to the show but as an experiment.
Speaker 0: I'm not gonna do it during the meta moment, but I just want to call it out here.
Speaker 0: Obviously, we're living in a really fucked up time right now And those are the other day have to do what we can.
Speaker 0: So instead of doing my you've the stingers I've been doing for the last several years at the end of the show where I usually just try to make a joke or something I'm going to consistently
Speaker 1: always
Speaker 0: give a Specific thing you can do that might actually matter like a real form of activism You can do every single episode of geek nights.
Speaker 0: It might be something tiny because it's hard to come up with these things.
Speaker 0: act activism.
Speaker 1: Number one Don't die.
Speaker 0: Yep.
Speaker 0: You got to survive.
Speaker 0: that is like that.
Speaker 1: Oh That is the number one thing that if you can't do if you don't have any energy or resources To do anything else or even if you do have the energy and resources to do other things not die is the first priority.
Speaker 1: Yep, if you can live then we can talk about other things Is not die.
Speaker 1: Concentrate on that.
Speaker 1: priority.
Speaker 0: number two is make sure you still find joy.
Speaker 0: Like if they demoralize you and you don't even enjoy your life Then they've kind of won like you've got it.
Speaker 1: that also puts you at risk of dying.
Speaker 1: So don't do that.
Speaker 0: But so to give you an example The one I'm gonna put at the end of the show is there's a specific Senate bill in New York That is very likely to pass if we get the state Senate and the state assembly to pass it.
Speaker 1: Yeah, the governor just turn it on it.
Speaker 1: Yeah, this one governor The governor is like, I don't know about this now because she thinks that if she doesn't do this That'll help negotiate for the congestion pricing.
Speaker 1: and it's like bro.
Speaker 1: Did you not know about?
Speaker 0: About how the Republicans are Lucy with the football.
Speaker 0: They will never leave the foot I learned.
Speaker 1: I learned about appeasement in like middle school.
Speaker 1: Yeah, you know appeasing.
Speaker 0: We did a whole unit how Neville Chamberlain fucked up badly.
Speaker 1: Yeah So regardless the governor is trying to appease this thing out of existence, but I think we should do it.
Speaker 0: Well what this thing is and I'll talk about it more in the end bit.
Speaker 0: But basically it would let the governor of New York delay special elections for the federal house until the general election Which would as I have the result because of how evil people have been appointed into positions in the regime Would reduce the margin the Republicans have in the House of Representatives by one which is a big fucking deal Because of how thin that majority they have is and it would deny them some key votes all the way until November this year.
Speaker 0: Like that's not nothing.
Speaker 0: and Hakeem Jeffries the minority leader in the house.
Speaker 0: Who is a stand-up dude has Heavily endorsed not perfect, but you know, he's nobody's perfect.
Speaker 0: That's the you know, that's something, you know totally.
Speaker 1: he didn't like the congestion pricing.
Speaker 1: Yeah I'll say if you wonder how he's thinking about that now though, if you expect perfection out of your politicians Honestly, you're a moron.
Speaker 0: You've just got to cheat you of all the options.
Speaker 0: You have to pick the best one of the options.
Speaker 0: It's kind of like with power it.
Speaker 0: the options aren't coal power or nothing No externalities nuclear power or no externalities.
Speaker 0: The options are coal power or nuclear power.
Speaker 0: They both suck.
Speaker 0: pick the one that sucks less What.
Speaker 0: the third option is no power.
Speaker 0: So it's that kind of situation.
Speaker 0: your foot no politicians gonna be perfect.
Speaker 0: Sometimes you gotta swallow your bile and vote for the one who's not a fascist.
Speaker 0: Like the French you're doing and the Germans are doing and the Spanish are doing almost That.
Speaker 1: the French air French are struggling.
Speaker 1: There's a French the French.
Speaker 0: They're like.
Speaker 1: all three of those are struggling.
Speaker 0: They're struggling but they are still holding the line, but just barely like 51%.
Speaker 0: for how long?
Speaker 0: Hey the longer you hold out that like that's that's that's how you fight these battles.
Speaker 0: It's a marathon.
Speaker 0: It's not a spring.
Speaker 0: We're not gonna win this tomorrow.
Speaker 0: So anyway at the end of the show every show there will be something you can do.
Speaker 0: However, small I'm gonna try to just do that and see how it goes.
Speaker 0: So let's dive right in electronic payments Which did not really exist in a meaningful form for me when I was a child.
Speaker 1: Well that when we were a chap, I mean, you know, I had to buy like my first computer.
Speaker 1: I was like Writing I was like ordering things online and then mailing checks.
Speaker 1: cuz yeah I have like a credit card.
Speaker 0: when I got my first fan subs, you know anime fan subs Like I didn't.
Speaker 0: I didn't even have a checking account.
Speaker 0: So I had to get my parents to help me get a money order and then I mailed this money order to some guy Who happened to be trustworthy enough and V kill did mail me like 20 VHS tapes of about a month later.
Speaker 1: Yeah, I mean even in the earliest days of credit cards, right the Diners Club card being like the first one It's like those weren't Electronic payments.
Speaker 0: Yeah, you know credit cards have those those raised numbers.
Speaker 0: I don't think you guys realize you know what those raised numbers are for.
Speaker 0: that is so.
Speaker 0: the way credit cards were processed is someone would take the credit card from you and Usually go to a back room somewhere and put it on a physical device that had carbon paper on it and they'd like go Shashank and it would take an imprint of the numbers of the credit card and then they would build those up and like once a week Or once a month, they'd send them all to visa
Speaker 1: Mm-hmm
Speaker 0: like that and only recently did that fall back.
Speaker 0: Stop being used.
Speaker 0: that was in use for certain cases up until not that long ago Like I want to say 2010s.
Speaker 0: That was still an option Mm-hmm.
Speaker 1: So yeah, it took quite a while before there were actually Electronic payments of any kind.
Speaker 1: Yep And the biggest thing is really is the ECH which is called.
Speaker 1: you might see this unlike your your bank account Statements like you know, like debit ECH or whatever it stands for electronic clearinghouse.
Speaker 1: And so what happened is back in the day way before there was you know credit cards or anything at debits or anything like that.
Speaker 1: there was Checks and you would write a check to somebody and that person would take that check to the bank right and The bank would say a check from Scott for $100.
Speaker 1: It said that means that $100 from Scott's bank can come over to our bank.
Speaker 1: Obviously if we have the same bank, the bank would just take care of that right there because they could see both accounts.
Speaker 1: But what if I had a different bank than you.
Speaker 1: that means my banks got to send money to your bank?
Speaker 1: Yeah, and to make that happen, right?
Speaker 1: And so what they would do is they had the thing called a clearinghouse where everyone would add up Basically, right how much I'm owed this much money from that bank But I owe this much money to that bank, right.
Speaker 1: and so the other bank does the same thing.
Speaker 1: and And then they come together at the clearinghouse at the end of the day or whatever and they go Aha you we did all our math and adding up all the checks together You owe us this much money and it's like well we added up all this and you owe us this much money.
Speaker 1: So then we add those numbers together and it turns out I owe you five cents.
Speaker 1: All right, we're done, right?
Speaker 1: We don't got to mess with all that other bullshit of doing each and every check.
Speaker 1: I just figured out the total and we cleared it and it's obviously way more complicated than that to the point of you know A lot of wrongness and I'm sure they financial experts would be like ravel ravel ravel But from a bird's-eye view that's how it worked.
Speaker 0: But what was interesting is that this slowed the course of just commerce among people.
Speaker 0: We're not talking about so much buying things from stores because online shopping and like the electronic payments that enable that are a different thing.
Speaker 0: But imagine even just passing money between people.
Speaker 0: I want to give Scott some money.
Speaker 0: It was either mail cash mail a check or do something complicated and expensive.
Speaker 0: but it also had all these like interesting side effects like There used to be the concept of floating a check.
Speaker 0: So like I write a check to Scott But let's say I only have $100 in my bank account I write a check to Scott for $80 and then I write a check to Emily for $80.
Speaker 0: I It'll be kind of random which one of them gets paid and which one of them has the check bounces Depending on like the order they get processed which banks are involved, etc.
Speaker 0: But a common practice for a very long time in like industrialized countries was write checks You know are bad because money will come into your account before those checks get processed.
Speaker 0: So like I know I'm gonna get my paycheck on Tuesday.
Speaker 0: The odds are the check I wrote to Scott and Emily won't both get processed before I get paid
Speaker 1: Yep, and so eventually, I don't know when I'm sure I could look it up But there's the ACH the automated clearinghouse and that's what basically enabled debit cards to come into existence And it's really.
Speaker 1: it's a thing from the US Treasury And it's like yeah Here's a whole bunch of rules and all kinds of documents that are way too complicated And so it's probably it's.
Speaker 1: it is someone's whole job Several people's whole jobs just manage this fucking thing where they automated the clearinghouse Instead of it being a manual thing.
Speaker 1: that happened every so often.
Speaker 1: it's automatic with computers and that's why when you get a direct deposit or whatever or you send someone money to you know with you Pay with a debit card.
Speaker 1: It says ACH on your bank statement because it's doing the automated clearinghouse You effectively are just writing checks.
Speaker 1: The checks are just completely digital and Instead of doing the old-school clearinghouse at the end of the day It's happening constantly all the time and computers are doing it so that nobody gets hosed.
Speaker 0: Now, this is important.
Speaker 0: This is a principle that I think a lot of younger people and tech pros don't quite understand that If you have a big complicated system and you want to migrate to a new fancy version of that system it is almost always a bad idea to design a new system entirely from scratch a Very good way to approach that kind of thing.
Speaker 0: Like Scott just said you basically Check still work the same way.
Speaker 0: You just try to automate parts of it Internal to a process that don't affect the endpoints of that process and then later you change how the endpoints work.
Speaker 0: Or if the endpoints of the problem change how the endpoints work.
Speaker 0: Let's not do checks Let's do something else but keep the internal process the same way it was before and then fix that later.
Speaker 0: Don't try to change everything all at once.
Speaker 0: that is almost always a disaster.
Speaker 0: that is proposed by someone young who is Inexperienced or a tech bro who doesn't know how anything other than tech for stuff works.
Speaker 1: That's right.
Speaker 1: And so this is why when you go to say send your friend money with PayPal, it'll be like Hey, do you want to send the money right the fuck now?
Speaker 1: or for we'll charge you a fee though But if you just wait a little bit one to three days $0.
Speaker 1: and that reason is if you wait one to three days They're gonna use a CH to make that transfer which is effectively the same as writing a check which costs nothing.
Speaker 1: It doesn't we don't make.
Speaker 1: I guess way back in the day There might have been checking fees sometimes but not anymore.
Speaker 1: that hasn't been a thing for a long time, right?
Speaker 1: And so you write chat.
Speaker 1: You can write all the checks you want as long as you have the money in your bank account to back it up and it Doesn't cost you a damn thing.
Speaker 1: It's totally free.
Speaker 1: and so you're paying someone with ACH with a digital check is also free, but it won't be instant because Clearing house so and there are other kinds of checks and things that are sort of like out of scope at this episode.
Speaker 0: But there was also the concept of wiring money which existed before The checks that we described and still exists today To a degree.
Speaker 0: but basically that was a way you do.
Speaker 0: we'd have computers you would.
Speaker 0: if you wanted to wire money You would go to a bank.
Speaker 1: Well, literally you could telegraph money.
Speaker 1: That was what Western Union be like And send money to people.
Speaker 0: Yeah, like if you needed to send cash to someone.
Speaker 0: like when I was a kid I remember one time having to wire money to Western Union like through Western Union.
Speaker 0: So someone I knew could go to a Western Union in a different state and get cash from that Western Union Because they needed that cash to get home Yeah, and effect the way that works is basically you go to a Western Union and you trust Western Union.
Speaker 1: yep, because they exist right and you trust that they're not just gonna rob you and You give Western Union money like here is money Western Union.
Speaker 1: Here is a hundred bucks and they say thanks We.
Speaker 1: now Western Union's total bank account has increased by a hundred bucks.
Speaker 0: Yep, so then they tell Office, okay, give this guy a hundred bucks.
Speaker 1: We're gonna give him like 90 bucks.
Speaker 0: Yeah They charged a lot Right.
Speaker 1: It's basically you want to give money to someone who's far away.
Speaker 1: well just put money in our Gigantic bank account and we will put less than that amount in whoever's bank account.
Speaker 1: you tell us to yeah Someone else at a different office comes in and they say hey Scott, I'm in I'm in I don't know the Antarctica Yeah, and Scott in New York.
Speaker 1: He he said he sent me a hundred but he sent me a hundred bucks.
Speaker 1: And the Western Union says, oh well We're the same company and we have a telegraph to communicate with each other and I did receive a telegraph from New York.
Speaker 1: That said yes Western Union in New York Confirms that Scott gave us a hundred bucks and that means I can give you 90 bucks and we're gonna keep 10 bucks.
Speaker 1: Yeah, cuz that's what we do for the for the service.
Speaker 0: So wiring money was this situation outside of a Western Union you could do with banks, too And they would also charge a lot.
Speaker 0: and this was for like let's say you're buying a house and you got to give a down payment.
Speaker 0: you could either get a kill like a special kind of check like a cashier's check or a certified check and then you physically bring that or mail it and do a whole thing or You could go to your bank and say I want to wire money to this address like this Individual.
Speaker 0: and that was a bank thing that would also cost a lot of money But did become electronic pretty early, even though sometimes a check would pop out the other end and it was generally otherwise like really hard to transfer money between people without paying a lot of money or waiting for these things to process.
Speaker 0: the world we live in now is Radically different like it is hard to overstate how radical PayPal was When it appeared the fact that you could kind of just pass money around.
Speaker 0: I've never had a PayPal account because it was so radical.
Speaker 1: I didn't trust it and I didn't trust it for a long time.
Speaker 1: But now I use it.
Speaker 0: Yeah, I've never used it.
Speaker 1: actually It's the good thing about PayPal.
Speaker 1: Obviously, there's a lot of bad things.
Speaker 1: The good thing about PayPal is that if you go to some shady ass website all right to like buy an e like ecommerce like a little web store, right and That web store is like hey, I'm like your local indie bookstore.
Speaker 1: buy a book directly from me And it's like I love you indie bookstore.
Speaker 1: I know that you're a legitimate business.
Speaker 1: I know that you will send me a book if I give you money But your voice is gonna get ransomed.
Speaker 0: where then someone's gonna?
Speaker 0: you
Speaker 1: got some janky ass website that you got set up here and you want me to type my credit card number into that janky website with no HTTPS or who knows what software you're running by yourself and how it's compromised and you want my actual credit card number into that website.
Speaker 1: I can be then harvested by who knows the hell.
Speaker 1: it's like no PayPal.
Speaker 1: who has a big company which has secure computers.
Speaker 1: They know my credit card number and they will do some token e encrypted biz.
Speaker 1: that's secure and you will get the money but you will.
Speaker 1: your Untrustworthy website will never know my actual credit card number and that is why I will use a PayPal or similar type service.
Speaker 0: true cuz back then there weren't really many places that would do the thing like a temporary disposable credit card every time you do a transaction like.
Speaker 0: there's a lot of cool ways to handle that problem.
Speaker 0: now PayPal is just one among many.
Speaker 0: But I think the big revolution Was Apple pay.
Speaker 0: in this.
Speaker 0: I and I go Android and like Google kind of followed along and I don't want to get into a little History of it, but nowadays the fact that I can just like basically text Scott money and it just works That is a relatively new development in human history.
Speaker 1: Oh, yeah, I Mean, you know the way it works isn't really too different from say like a Western Union kind of situation, right?
Speaker 1: It's like, you know and or PayPal isn't really any different.
Speaker 1: when you get right down to it.
Speaker 1: it's like you have this intermediary company and You can give them money and then they give money to the other person who also is You know as business with them.
Speaker 1: Yep, right and that's you.
Speaker 1: you're not transferring the money Actually directly from you to your friend.
Speaker 1: You could you know, even if you did that like with a. the only way to do that I guess is with cash.
Speaker 1: Yes Even if you go to a bank and like you use your bank account numbers and you write checks to give money to each other You're using a CH.
Speaker 1: using the bank is the intermediary.
Speaker 1: there's always some intermediary unless you just hand cash to your friend.
Speaker 1: That's the only other way.
Speaker 0: Mm-hmm and I It actually kind of changed my life like in a lot of ways.
Speaker 0: like the fact that when we're at a restaurant like I remember In college if we had a dinner with a bunch of people trying to split up the check and like trying to pay and like someone doesn't have cash and three different people have credit cards or
Speaker 1: People don't have the right denominations of cash.
Speaker 0: Yeah the fact that now like we'll go to a dinner one of those they'll just put a credit card down and then Literally can just invoice everyone else like the split check and just get paid Automatically and
Speaker 1: you don't have to harass the the wait staff to split the check and do all kinds of math or whatever.
Speaker 0: But also now a lot of restaurants.
Speaker 0: finally the u.s.
Speaker 0: Is catching up in this regard almost every restaurant we go to now.
Speaker 0: They will come out with a little device and say about half I'd say most of the ones I go to the notable one that won't is a turn us all.
Speaker 0: they only take cash or MX Interest.
Speaker 1: that's really limited.
Speaker 0: Yeah, it is really limited.
Speaker 0: Yeah, I would say the majority of times I've ever gone there I forgot that fact and then like had to go to the ATM and get cash and come back because I only got an MX Kind of recently.
Speaker 1: you always worry about a restaurant that has an ATM in the restaurant.
Speaker 0: Oh, yeah.
Speaker 0: Oh, yeah That's.
Speaker 0: that's either a strip club a tax dodge Mafia front.
Speaker 0: Yeah or turn us all in Queens.
Speaker 0: But actually they don't even have an ATM which is the worst.
Speaker 0: you have to like go down the street and find an ATM.
Speaker 0: but the other thing a lot of those places are doing now is They'll either have a QR code.
Speaker 0: You can just scan.
Speaker 0: that takes you to a payment thing Like that's cropping up especially in Europe.
Speaker 0: I'm seeing that everywhere but - they don't care about split checks anymore.
Speaker 0: They'll be like how much do you want who pays for what?
Speaker 0: and just swipe all the credit cards and the little device actually just Handles it pretty nicely like.
Speaker 0: it's just interesting how This space moved so slowly for so long and then just in the last few years.
Speaker 0: It is like rapidly accelerated the quality of life improvements of the user experience of making digital cash transactions in person.
Speaker 1: You know, it's like we've had.
Speaker 1: you know, the credit cards that you know Basically visa MasterCard, whoever was processing the payments and charging a fee and charging the merchants a fee And they still do that and that's still everywhere, but you couldn't use credit cards to give money to like your friend.
Speaker 0: Yeah, I mean credit cards if you wanted money instead of buying something from a commercial institution.
Speaker 0: There's a thing called a cash advance.
Speaker 0: That is a bad idea in almost all cases.
Speaker 0: I don't even know if all credit cards still do it.
Speaker 1: I think if you yeah, if you put your credit card in an ATM, you can probably get cash out of the ATM if you know your pin.
Speaker 1: Yeah, but remember that's not cash that you have right?
Speaker 1: That's why there's no clearinghouse because it's not cash that someone has this alone.
Speaker 1: Yeah, it's usually like a way bigger interest rate than your credit card has normally Yeah and there's usually crazy fees like I would look if you look through that giant fine print credit card documentation that you get when you Sign up for a new card.
Speaker 1: It's in there somewhere.
Speaker 1: Like if you can cash advance.
Speaker 1: Yeah what the limit is what the fees are.
Speaker 1: It's really almost never a good idea.
Speaker 1: only do it in an absolute emergency.
Speaker 0: It's only buried in the same section.
Speaker 0: that's like did you know you get car insurance if you rent a car and you follow all these specific rules?
Speaker 0: Yeah but Yeah, it's.
Speaker 0: it's.
Speaker 0: the space is continuing to evolve.
Speaker 0: The listener actually pointed something out that I thought I think we should touch on.
Speaker 0: the worst part about paper Was just that I helped enrich the worst tech bros in history.
Speaker 0: Yeah, pretty much cuz PayPal was the first mover.
Speaker 0: They weren't great.
Speaker 0: They were just the first one.
Speaker 0: Other people are trying to do similar things.
Speaker 0: that this is a pattern in technology that we see time and time again.
Speaker 1: Yeah, but it's not something that like just any old schmo can do because you know.
Speaker 1: So the barrier to get in the payments game is so high that it's like, you know The competitors to PayPal are like, you know, you got your venmo.
Speaker 1: I guess kind of right.
Speaker 1: You got your.
Speaker 1: Apple pays your Amazon pays your Google pays But they don't.
Speaker 1: they don't all quite do exactly the same thing at your squares and your stripes.
Speaker 1: Yeah, but PayPal sort of does all of the above.
Speaker 1: It's like all of those other ones are doing like just a fraction of what the features that PayPal has.
Speaker 1: PayPal can do everything right.
Speaker 1: it does all the things which is the day.
Speaker 0: So you don't really want the everything out because like I've been to places in Asia that it's not the every it's.
Speaker 1: yeah It's not the everything app in that sense, but it's the everything money.
Speaker 1: Yeah Whereas you know like venmo pretty much only does the give money to your friend and Apple pay pretty much only does the.
Speaker 1: It's a business and I can pay them.
Speaker 1: Oh and Apple cash is actually a different thing to give money to your friend or it's you know But it's like PayPal does both of those.
Speaker 0: Yep, but I haven't at the point for a long time now where I Really never use cash like pretty much ever.
Speaker 1: It's it's really declining.
Speaker 1: I'm still of the opinion that cash needs to exist But I use it.
Speaker 1: I use it today
Speaker 0: Like to the point that I went to an ATM before kovat and I didn't have to go to an ATM until uh Actually, I went to an ATM Seven months ago was the first time I had to go to an ATM again since the beginning of the kovat pandemic.
Speaker 1: Yeah, I use I will use cash to give gifts to people.
Speaker 1: Mm-hmm.
Speaker 1: I use Cash like pay the housekeeper.
Speaker 0: Yep, when I remember I always try to care.
Speaker 0: I try to have some cash on me to tip people when I'm traveling who are hard to tip but who actually do hard work Like if someone's carrying my suitcases around and a cod and stuff like that Or like the shuttle driver taking into the airport.
Speaker 0: Yeah, this has been geek nights with rim and Scott.
Speaker 0: special thanks to DJ pretzel for the opening theme.
Speaker 1: Be sure to visit our website at front row.
Speaker 1: clue comm for show notes discussion links and more.
Speaker 0: Remember geek nights is not one but four different shows Monday's or science and technology Tuesday's.
Speaker 0: gaming and games Wednesday's or animation and comics Thursday's are arbitrary and indiscriminate.
Speaker 0: Geek nights is distributed under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 International license.
Speaker 1: geek nights is recorded live with no studio and no audience.
Speaker 1: But I'd like those other late shows.
Speaker 1: it's actually recorded at night
Speaker 0: and the patreon patrons for this episode of geek nights are Alan Joyce Linky G dread lily Tenebrae Chris had odd Christopher or Clinton Walton Finn Joel Hayes penny rhyme or Rebecca Don Sam Erickson sure from on All and a bunch of people who do not want me to say their names.
Speaker 0: Remember every geek nights episode will always be free on patreon using it more as a backup.
Speaker 0: But we appreciate your support and all the money that does come in goes into investing in more geek nights content Like the meta context stuff that we're putting a lot of effort into stay tuned for some stuff for me and Emily so in the final bit as threatened.
Speaker 0: So if you want to help and you live in New York State contact your New York State Assembly and state senate representatives as well as the governor of New York governor Hochul and Tell them you support Senate bill s 4 5 8 8. that is Senate bill s 4 5 8 8.
Speaker 0: I'll post a link in the forum.
Speaker 0: Basically, this bill will allow us to prevent the Republicans from having someone in in the house until November When the special election will be able to be called and it'll also give us time to field a good anti-fascist Democratic candidate to potentially win that seat.
Speaker 0: We need to convince the assembly and the Senate to pass this and we absolutely need to convince our middling and governor Hochul to sign this into law.
Speaker 0: This is a big deal.
Speaker 0: This could materially prevent some of the harm that's coming from the Republicans.
Speaker 0: I can't promise that every piece of activist advice I will give you as we do this new bid and geek nights will be as powerful as this one.
Speaker 0: But this is a big deal.
Speaker 0: It's going on right now.
Speaker 0: Check out the link in the forum.
Speaker 0: Write your people and I'll come up with something for Wednesday.
Speaker 0: So now that said I will still leave you with some fucking internet nonsense.
Speaker 0: Why is that?
Speaker 0: That's it now you're not You.